<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3661</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-03661-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Zinc-modified Calcium Silicate Coatings Promote Osteogenic Differentiation through TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad Pathway and Osseointegration in Osteopenic Rabbits</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Jiangming</given-names></name><address><email>yjm_st@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Lizhang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Ning</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Yanhai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Xuebin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xiongsheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Meiyan</given-names></name><address><email>061022049@fudan.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Xiaojian</given-names></name><address><email>yespine@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0369 1660</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.73113.37</institution-id><institution>Department of Orthopaedics, </institution><institution>Changzheng Hospital of Second Military Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, 200003 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000119573309</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9227.e</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Inorganic Coating Materials, Shanghai Institute of Ceramics, </institution><institution>Chinese Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, 200050 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0369 6365</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.22069.3f</institution-id><institution>Shanghai Key Laboratory of Regulatory Biology, Institute of Biomedical Sciences and School of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>East China Normal University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, 200241 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>National Engineering Research Center for Nanotechnology, Shanghai, 200241 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>3440</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p>Surface-modified metal implants incorporating different ions have been employed in the biomedical field as bioactive dental implants with good osseointegration properties. However, the molecular mechanism through which surface coatings exert the biological activity is not fully understood, and the effects have been difficult to achieve, especially in the osteopenic bone. In this study, We examined the effect of zinc-modified calcium silicate coatings with two different Zn contents to induce osteogenic differentiation of rat bone marrow-derived pericytes (BM-PCs) and osteogenetic efficiency in ovariectomised rabbits. Ti-6Al-4V with zinc-modified calcium silicate coatings not only enhanced proliferation but also promoted osteogenic differentiation and mineralized matrix deposition of rat BM-PCs as the zinc content and culture time increased <italic>in vitro</italic>. The associated molecular mechanisms were investigated by Q-PCR and Western blotting, revealing that TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway plays a direct and significant role in regulating BM-PCs osteoblastic differentiation on Zn-modified coatings. Furthermore, <italic>in vivo</italic> results that revealed Zn-modified calcium silicate coatings significantly promoted new bone formation around the implant surface in osteopenic rabbits as the Zn content and exposure time increased. Therefore, Zn-modified calcium silicate coatings can improve implant osseointegration in the condition of osteopenia, which may be beneficial for patients suffering from osteoporosis-related fractures.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>Osteoporosis is a chronic bone disease impacting the general population and characterized by compromised bone strength predisposing to increased fracture risk. Metal implants are used to support prosthetic devices including dental implants in the biomedical field. However, these metal implants are susceptible to corrosion, leading to implant loosening, wear and poor loading<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>, especially in osteoporotic patients, which could cause a reduction in the support ability of an implant due to decreased bone mass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. To overcome these issues, various strategies have been investigated. Coating the surface with bioactive components appears to be a promising way to improve the osseointegration of metal implants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Calcium phosphate, including hydroxyapatite (HA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, coatings applied on titanium implants enhance the bone integration of metal implants compared to uncoated implants. However, the biological and mechanical fixation differed substantially for coated implants in osteoporotic bones and normal bones<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Hence, there is a need to modify these implants so that they can form strong bonds with the host tissue, especially in clinically challenging scenarios, such as osteoporosis due to low bone mass density and strength.</p><p>In recent years, titanium surfaces have been modified by incorporating different ions to improve the mechanical fixation of implants to bone. Zinc is a structural constituent of some proteins, including enzymes belonging to cellular signaling pathways and transcription factors, that stimulates osteoblastic cell proliferation, differentiation and mineralization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Supplementation with zinc may be important in the prevention of osteoporosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Some studies have shown that Zn, Mg and Sr ion implants stimulated osteoblastic cell proliferation and had positive effects on osseointegration in both healthy or pathological bone<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Moreover, another reports have suggested that incorporation of dopant ions into bio-glass, Ca-P, and Ca-Si ceramics with certain dosage positively affected the cellular responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Although scientifically promising, the molecular mechanism underlying the effects of the ion-doped bioactive coatings on bone-forming cells is not fully understood.</p><p>Bone marrow-derived pericytes (BM-PCs) as a population of progenitor cells are able to differentiate into several types of cells, including endothelial cells and osteocytic cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, which are used in promising cellular therapies in regenerative medicine. In the present study, We used BM pericytes to investigate the effect of Ca<sub>2</sub>ZnSi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub> coatings with different Zn/Ca ratios on proliferation and osteogenic differentiation <italic>in vitro</italic> and the associated molecular mechanisms. Moreover, we evaluated the osteogenic potential of these coatings in osteopenic rabbits. We found that Ca<sub>2</sub>ZnSi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub> coatings with higher Zn content significantly increased the cell proliferation, osteogenic differentiation genes expression and the mineralized matrix deposition. In addition, Ca<sub>2</sub>ZnSi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub> coatings activated the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad pathway during the osteogenic differentiation of BM-PCs. Furthermore, <italic>in vivo</italic> tests revealed that Zn-modified calcium silicate coatings had a significant influence on the new bone formation around the implant surface as the Zn-Ca ratio and the exposure time increased in osteopenic rabbits. The results could provide valuable information for future studies aimed to exploit positive ion-modified coatings for bone tissue engineering, especially for clinically challenging diseases such as osteoporosis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Effects of Various Coatings on Cell Proliferation and Cytotoxicity</title><p>BM-PCs were seeded and grown on Ti-6Al-4V (control), CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, and Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3 coatings. After 1, 4, 7 and 14 days, cell proliferation was determined using the Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8) assay (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). Cell proliferation increased with the culture time and Zn content, but no difference was observed on the initial day of culture. After 4, 7 and 14 days of culture, more BM-PCs were found on the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating than on the Zn-Ca 0.1 and CaSiO<sub>3</sub> coatings and the Ti-6Al-4V control. In addition, the cell cytotoxicity on the various coatings at 48&#x02009;h was evaluated by a live/dead-staining assay. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>, most BM-PCs were stained green in color and had almost no dead red-stained cells. This result was similar to that of the proliferation assay. Among all the samples, those with the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating had the largest number of living cells. Together, It has been well demonstrated that the release of suitable concentration of zinc could stimulate cell proliferation <italic>in vitro</italic>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) BM-PCs proliferation on the Ti-6Al-4V (control) and the CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3 coating surfaces for 1, 4, 7 and 14 days as measured by a CCK-8 assay. (<bold>B</bold>) Cell cytotoxicity of BM-PCs cultured on different coatings at 48&#x02009;h. Data are presented as the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;6). *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_3661_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e450"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Effect of Zinc-modified Coatings on Osteogenic Marker Expression</title><p>The expression of the specific osteogenic markers alkaline phosphatase (ALP), procollagen &#x003b1;1(I) (Col-I), osteocalcin (OCN) and runt-related transcription factor 2 (RUNX-2) was examined using quantitative polymerase chain reaction (Q-PCR). A detailed presentation of the fold change in the expression of these markers is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. For each experiment, BM-PCs were cultured on Ti-6Al-4V with the growth medium as a negative control, which had no detectable levels of the osteogenesis-specific genes. In addition, osteogenic differentiation was induced on Ti-6Al-4V exposed to osteogenic medium, which served as a positive control and expressed osteogenesis-related genes. The expression of an early stage osteoblast differentiation marker, ALP, was upregulated in BM-PCs cultured on the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating compared to cells cultured on the other coatings and the control, with maximum upregulation at day 14 for all treatment groups. However, at day 21, the ALP levels were lower than the mRNA expression observed on other days, and no significant difference was found at day 1. Col-I is also an early marker of osteogenic differentiation. The Col-I mRNA expression level decreased from day 7 for all samples, but the levels were significantly higher in cells seeded on the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating than those on the Zn-Ca 0.1 coating, the CaSiO<sub>3</sub> coating and the control. The expression levels of the late osteogenic marker OCN increased in all groups with a time-dependent effect and significant upregulation for the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating compared with the Zn-Ca 0.1 coating, the CaSiO<sub>3</sub> coating and the control at all time points. A similar trend was observed for the RUNX-2 mRNA expression.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Quantitative real-time PCR analysis of the ALP, Col-I, OCN and RUNX-2 mRNA expression on different coatings at four time points (1, 7, 14 and 21 days). Data were calculated relative to the expression of the housekeeping gene GAPDH, which was used as the internal control. The results are presented as the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD for triplicate measurements. *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001. Abbreviations: GAPDH, glyceraldehyde phosphate dehydrogenase; ALP, alkaline phosphatase; Col-I, procollagen &#x003b1;1(I); OCN, osteocalcin; RUNX-2, runt-related transcription factor 2. Negative control: BM-PCs on Ti-6Al-4V with growth medium. Positive control: BM-PCs on Ti-6Al-4V with osteogenic medium.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_3661_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e483"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Zinc-modified Coatings Promote the Osteogenic Differentiation and Mineralization of BM-PCs</title><p>BM-PCs cultured on various coatings were subjected to an ELISA assay. The ALP activity levels had a similar profile for all samples, with increased activity during the differentiation of BM-PCs into osteoblasts at all time points (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>). The expression of ALP was upregulated to its highest levels after 14 days and then downregulated after 21 days in all samples. However, the enzymatic activity of ALP was significantly increased in BM-PCs cultured on the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating compared to the other groups.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) ALP activity and (<bold>B</bold>) Col-I and (<bold>C</bold>) OCN levels of BM-PCs cultured on Ti-6Al-4V (control) and on the CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3 coating surfaces with or without the osteogenic medium at 1, 7, 14 and 21 days. (<bold>D</bold>) Semi-quantitative analysis of <italic>in vitro</italic> matrix deposition mineralization was performed at 21 days by Alizarin red S staining. Negative control: BM-PCs on Ti-6Al-4V with growth medium. Positive control: BM-PCs on Ti-6Al-4V with osteogenic medium. Each value represents the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from triplicate determinations.*<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_3661_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e529"/></fig>
</p><p>Col-I levels were determined at 1, 7, 14 and 21 days of culture (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>). The Col-I level decreased with time for all groups from 7 to 21 days, and no significant difference was found between all groups on the first day of culture. However, higher levels of Col-I were observed in cells cultured on the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating than in the other coating groups and the control group, and the level increased with the Zn/Ca ratio.</p><p>OCN was also used to evaluate the effect on the osteogenic differentiation of BM-PCs on different coatings <italic>in vitro</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3C</xref>). In the BM-PCs grown on all coatings, the OCN level increased with culture time. Moreover, cells on the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating at 21 days had significantly greater OCN levels than the other coating groups and the control group, although there was no significant difference in OCN levels in all groups at day 1. All the results showed striking similarities with the Q-PCR analysis, which suggested that the Zn-Ca 0.3 coatings have higher potential to induce the differentiation of BM-PCs into osteoblasts than all other groups.</p><p>To evaluate the osteogenic mineralization of the BM-PCs on the various coatings, Alizarin red S staining was employed to assess calcium deposition using a semi-quantitative analysis of cells at day 21 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3D</xref>). The amount of calcium deposition was greatly increased in the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating group compared to all other groups. In addition, the level of mineralized deposition increased as the Zn-Ca ratio increased.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Enhancement of the Osteogenic Differentiation of BM-PCs Cultured on Zn-modified Coatings through the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad Signaling Pathway</title><p>To understand the molecular mechanisms by which Zn-modified coatings promote osteogenic differentiation in BM-PCs, we first screened several signaling pathways associated with BM-PCs differentiation by Q-PCR. Several signaling pathways play significant roles in the regulation osteogenic differentiation on different surface coatings, including insulin-like factor-1 (IGF-1), mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) and transforming growth factor-&#x003b2;1(TGF-&#x003b2;1) signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. In our study, the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway played an essential role in the regulation of BM-PCs osteogenic differentiation. The Q-PCR results showed that the mRNA levels of TGF-&#x003b2;1, Smad2 and Smad3 all increased with incubation time for all coatings. Moreover, the associated genes were significantly increased in the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating compared with that of the other groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref>). However, no substantial enhancement with culture time was observed for the expression of genes in the classical MAPK signaling pathway, including insulin-like growth factor (IGF-I), extracellular signalregulated kinase1/2 (ERK 1/2) and protein kinase C-&#x003b4; (PKC-&#x003b4;), for any of the coatings (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Therefore, our data indicated that Zn-modified coatings appeared to specifically and significantly activate the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway during the osteogenic differentiation of BM-PCs.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Detection of genes and proteins involved in the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway. (<bold>A</bold>) Q-PCR quantification of genes involved in the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway in BM-PCs cultured on Ti-6Al-4V (control) and on the CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3 coating surfaces at 1, 7, 14 and 21 days. The results were determined by the comparative CT method (2<sup>&#x02212;<italic>&#x00394;&#x00394;</italic>CT</sup>). The bars represent the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001. (<bold>B</bold>) Western blot analysis of the expression of Smad2/3 and phosphorylated Smad2/3 in BM-PCs cultured on Ti-6Al-4V (control) and on the CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3 coatings for 21 days in the presence or absence of the ALK5 inhibitor SB431542 (10&#x02009;&#x003bc;M). GAPDH served as an internal control. Negative control: BM-PCs on Ti-6Al-4V with growth medium. Positive control: BM-PCs on Ti-6Al-4V with osteogenic medium.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_3661_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e603"/></fig>
</p><p>The effect of Zn-modified coatings on TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway activation was further verified by Western blotting assays (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>). Typically, receptor-regulated Smad (R-Smad) is activated by phosphorylation upon TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling. The expression levels of key proteins involved in the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway, including Smad2/3 and p-Smad2/3, were increased in the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating group compared to the other groups. In addition, SB431542, a highly selective inhibitor of Smad2/Smad3, was used. As expected, treatment with SB431542 decreased the Smad2/3 and p-Smad2/3 protein levels in a manner consistent with the effects of SB431542. This result suggests that the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway plays a direct and significant role in regulating BM-PCs osteogenic differentiation on the different coatings, while neither the IGF-1pathway nor the MAPK pathway appear to be involved.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Effects of Zinc-modified Coatings on Bone Regeneration <italic>In Vivo</italic></title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Micro-CT Evaluation</title><p>To investigate the effects of Zn-modified coatings on bone regeneration in osteopenic rabbits, bare (control) and hydroxyapatite (HA)-, CaSiO<sub>3</sub>-, Zn-Ca0.1- and Zn-Ca0.3-coated Ti-6Al-4V with a diameter of 2.0&#x02009;mm and a length of 10&#x02009;mm was implanted into the femur defects of osteopenic rabbits subjected to bilateral ovariectomy (OVX) in combination with methylprednisolone sodium succinate (MPS) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). 3-D micro-CT was used to evaluate the differences in the bone-implant interface and trabecular microstructure of peri-implant bone tissue between the control and treated groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). At 1 month post-implantation, almost no new bone formation was apparent in the control or the HA and CaSiO<sub>3</sub> coating groups, and a better performance of bone repair and integrity was found in the Zn-modified coating groups with increases in the Zn/Ca ratio. From 2 to 3 months post-implantation, all groups showed enhanced bone formation with implant time. 3D images indicated that the bone density on the surface of the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating was enhanced compared to that of the Ti-6Al-4V control and other coating groups. The osteogenic effect was in the order Zn-Ca 0.3&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Zn-Ca 0.1&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;CaSiO<sub>3</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;HA&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;control. This result suggests that the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating had the strongest promoting effect on bone formation with implant time.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>3-D micro-CT analysis for the assessment of newly formed bone tissue on the surface of Ti-6Al-4V and on hydroxyapatite (HA), CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3 coatings 1, 2, and 3 months after implantation in osteopenic rabbit femurs. (<bold>A</bold>) 3D images of trabecular bone (gray) on the surface of Ti-6Al-4V and HA, CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3 coatings (pink) at 1, 2, and 3 months post-implantation. White arrows indicate new bone formation. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantitative results of implant osseointegration and peri-implant microstructural parameters, such as bone mineral density, bone volume/total volume of bone, trabecular number, trabecular thickness and trabecular separation, on the surface obtained by micro-CT assessment 1, 2, and 3 months after implant insertion. All data are represented as the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_3661_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e666"/></fig>
</p><p>The comprehensive quantitative analysis of all the micro CT parameters is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>. At 1 month post-implantation, the Zn-modified coating resulted in slight changes in all micro-CT parameters. From 2 to 3 months post-implantation, the HA, CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3 coating groups displayed a significant increase in all structural bone parameters, including bone mineral density (BMD), bone volume/tissue volume (BV/TV), trabecular number (Tb.N), and trabecular thickness (Tb.Th) and a lower trabecular separation (Tb.Sp) than the control. Moreover, the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating had the strongest effect on these parameters, and significant differences appeared within all five groups, which provided support for the results of the micro-CT images.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Histological Analysis</title><p>The micro-CT analysis of the segmental defects was further supplemented by histological analysis. The photomicrographs of longitudinal sections of the bone defect sites of all coatings show the details of the bone-to-implant interface and peri-implant bone tissue (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The Ti-6Al-4V-implanted group did not form new bones along the integrated surfaces at 1 and 2 months post-implantation but did have a small amount of new bone formation away from the implant interface. Moreover, almost no osteointegration was observed around the implants at 3 months post-implantation. For the HA coating, a few new bones started to form at 1 month, more regenerated bone formed at some sites of the coating surfaces at 2 months, and limited osteointegration was found at 3 months post-implantation. Although new bone started to be induced in the CaSiO<sub>3</sub> coating at 1 month, more new bones were regenerated along the integrated surfaces at 2 months, and a few showed osteointegration at 3 months. The Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3 coating groups showed a prominent induction of new bone formation at 1 month, and a large amount of the new bone surrounding the implant was characterized by prominent osteoid seams at the surface of newly formed mineralized bone at 2, 3 months. In particular, we found that most of the new bone integrated with the coating surfaces in the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating group at 2 months, and all but the most recently formed bones were tightly integrated with the implantation surfaces at 3 months. Collectively, our results suggested that the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating improved osseointegration with the formation of a direct bone interface <italic>in vivo</italic>.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Histological, toluidine blue-stained sections from osteoporotic rabbits 1, 2, 3 months post-implantation for Ti-6Al-4V and the hydroxyapatite (HA), CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3 coatings. Right panel (Scale bar indicates 500&#x02009;&#x003bc;m): magnification of the left red square in panel (Scale bar indicates 1000&#x02009;&#x003bc;m) in each month. Im, implant; M, month.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_3661_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e701"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Calcium silicate (Ca-Si) ceramics have attracted great attention in bone tissue engineering because of their bioactivity and good osseointegration properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. However, there are still some drawbacks, including a relatively high dissolution rate in biological environments that affects long-term clinical performance especially in osteoporotic patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Thus, various surface modification methods have been used to enhance the chemical stability and biological properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Some studies have suggested that incorporation of dopant Zn ions into bioactive coatings with appropriate concentrations positively affected the cellular responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Higher zinc content could result in reduction in cell proliferation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. In this study, we successfully prepared Zn-modified calcium silicate coatings with different Zn contents on Ti-6Al-4V by the plasma-spray method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. We found that Zn modified titanium surface improved the osteogenic activity as the Zn/Ca mol ratio increased <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><p>Much research in bone tissue engineering has been devoted to adult stem cells. BM-PCs were used in the present study due to their high osteogenic capacity and clinical significance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Our results showed that Zn-modified coatings significantly enhance proliferation in BM-PCs and are non-cytotoxic compared with CaSiO<sub>3</sub> coatings and uncoated Ti-6Al-4V at all tested time points. Moreover, the cell proliferation rate correlated with the increase in the Zn/Ca mol ratio, consistent with our previous study and other studies reporting the stimulatory effect of zinc on osteoblastic cell behavior<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Therefore, the enhanced cell viability on the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating may be attributed to proper Zn release.</p><p>Previous research has demonstrated that osteoblast-specific factors might be important at several stages of bone regeneration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. In the present study, the osteogenic markers ALP, Col-I, OCN and RUNX-2 were chosen to examine osteogenic differentiation <italic>in vitro</italic> by Q-PCR. Compared to the Zn-Ca 0.1 coating, the CaSiO<sub>3</sub> coating and the control, the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating significantly upregulated osteogenesis-specific genes, such as ALP, Col-I, OCN and RUNX-2. ELISA analysis also indicated that the ALP activity and the Col-I and OCN secretion were stronger for BM-PCs on the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating than on the other coatings and the uncoated Ti-6Al-4V. Thus, notable differences in ALP, Col-I and OCN activity were related to the osteogenic effects of zinc. Similar results showing that various Zn concentrations have different effects on osteogenic differentiation were previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the effect of Zn-modified coatings on osteoblast differentiation was investigated by Alizarin red S staining. Bone nodules are osteoblastic phenotypic markers and represent the final stages of osteoblastic differentiation. Alizarin red S quantification revealed that the percentage of mineralized nodules increased with the Zn/Ca mol ratio and cells on the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating after 21 days had higher levels of calcium nodule formation than that in other groups. The results were in agreement with previous studies showing that Zn plays an important role in osteoblastic bone formation and mineralization and that Zn-containing implants could improve osteoblastic function through proper Zn-ion release<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. However, little is known about the mechanism underlying the Zn-modified coating promotion of osteogenic differentiation and bone regeneration.</p><p>To further investigate the underlying molecular mechanisms, we searched for potential target genes associated with signaling pathways of BM-PCs osteogenic differentiation on the different coatings. Our results showed that Zn-modified coatings upregulated genes of the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway, such as TGF-&#x003b2;1, Smad2 and Smad3. No change was observed with culture time for the expression of genes involved in the classical MAPK signaling pathway, including IGF-I, ERK 1/2 and PKC, in all the coatings, which suggested that Zn-modified coatings can activate the TGF-&#x003b2; signaling pathway and promote differentiation and mineralization in BM-PCs. The TGF-&#x003b2; pathway is important for BM-PCs differentiation into the osteogenic and chondrogenic lineages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. TGF-&#x003b2; affects bone formation by activating their receptors to induce the phosphorylation of a group of intracellular transcription factors known as Smads<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. <italic>Smad2/3</italic> serve as substrates for TGF-&#x003b2; receptors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. The activated Smad complex can then move into the nucleus to trigger the transcription of a set of target genes. In this study, the TGF-&#x003b2; inhibitor SB431542 was used to investigate the direct role of TGF-&#x003b2; signaling during the process of BM-PCs differentiation on the different coatings. Blocking TGF-&#x003b2; signaling resulted in reduced Smad2/3 and p-Smad2/3 protein levels, which indicated that the Smad2/3-mediated TGF-&#x003b2; signaling pathway is strongly involved in the Zn-modified coatings promoting differentiation and mineralization in BM-PCs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). In addition, Runt-related transcription factor 2 (RUNX-2) is the earliest osteogenic marker (<italic>Runx</italic>-<italic>2</italic>) that binds to the osteocalcin promoter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>, interacts with Smads and subsequently induces the osteogenic marker genes ALP and Col-I at early stages and OCN at later stages of differentiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. Our results further support the fact that TGF-&#x003b2; signaling is an important event in BM-PCs proliferation and differentiation in a Smad-3-dependent manner<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Plausible molecular mechanism of Zn-modified coatings modulating of osteogenic differentiation of BM-PCs through the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_3661_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e858"/></fig>
</p><p>For biomedical implants, improving bone regeneration on implant surfaces is an important issue for the long-term success of the implant in both healthy and pathological conditions. The mains studies on biomaterial implants were performed in healthy animals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. However, the effects of titanium implants in the presence of an osteoporotic state are rarely reported. The most significant problem in treating osteoporotic fractures is unstable fixation arising from implant loosening because of the poor bone stock with low implant pull-out strength<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. The major contribution of this study is that shows that Zn-modified titanium improves implant osseointegration in ovariectomized rabbits as a model of osteoporosis. In <italic>in vivo</italic> study, the micro-CT results showed that Zn-modified coatings with higher Zn content can promote new bone formation to repair an osteoporosis metaphysis bone defect at early (1 month) and late time points (3 months). This function is correlated with the Zn content of the coatings and the implant time. Coatings containing higher amounts of Zn significantly increased BMD, BV/TV, Tb.N and Tb.Th and significantly decreased Tb.Sp compared to those in the other groups. Furthermore, the histomorphometric results also showed tighter contact with the surrounding host bone tissue with no obvious adverse effects and with accelerated new bone formation around the coating surface for the Zn-Ca 0.3 coating compared to the other coatings and pure titanium. These findings suggest that the Zn ions released from the Ca-Si-based coatings could influence the surrounding bone tissue, specifically by regulating the osteogenesis-related parameters of the environment for better integration of the titanium substrate with the host bone tissue, which was consistent with the previous reports that Zn has a positive effect on osteoblastic activity and bone formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>. In other words, the Zn-modified coatings exhibited better properties for implant osseointegration in osteopenic rabbits and could have promising clinical potential for orthopedic implants, especially in the condition of osteoporosis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Zn-doped calcium silicate coatings with two different Zn contents were successfully prepared by plasma spraying. Zn-modified coatings significantly promoted the proliferation and osteogenic differentiation of BM-PCs <italic>in vitro</italic>, showing a remarkable increase in osteogenesis-specific gene markers, such as ALP, Col-I, OCN and RUNX-2, and higher levels of ALP activity, Col-I and OCN secretion and calcium deposition with obvious dose- and time-dependent tendencies. Moreover, we confirmed that Zn-modified coatings activated the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling pathway to regulate BM-PCs osteoblastic differentiation. Furthermore, the <italic>in vivo</italic> study demonstrated that Zn-modified coatings with a higher Zn content significantly enhanced bone contact and regeneration with host bone tissue in osteopenic rabbits. These findings suggested that Zn-modified coatings are good candidates with high potential for clinical applications for treating defective osteoporotic bone tissues in the future.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Experimental Section</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Preparation and Characterization of Ca-Si-based Powders and Coatings</title><p>Zn-modified calcium silicate ceramic powders were synthesized using a previously described method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Briefly, zinc nitrate hexahydrate (Zn(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O; Sinopharm Chemical Reagent Co., Ltd.(SCRC), Shanghai, China), calcium nitrate tetrahydrate (Ca(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>.4H<sub>2</sub>O; SCRC, Shanghai, China) and tetraethyl orthosilicate (TEOS, (C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>O)<sub>4</sub>Si); SCRC, Shanghai, China) were used as raw materials. In the process, the mol ratio of Zn(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O:Ca(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>.4H<sub>2</sub>O:C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>O)<sub>4</sub>Si was x:1:1,with values of x&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1 and 0.3 (denoted by Zn-Ca 0.1 and Zn-Ca 0.3, respectively). An atmospheric plasma-spraying (APS) system (F4-MB, Sulzer Metco, Switzerland) was used to fabricate the coatings on Ti-6Al-4 V (Shanghai Yantai Metallic Material Co., Ltd., China) substrate with dimensions of &#x000f8; 10&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1&#x02009;mm and &#x000f8; 10&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2&#x02009;mm for the <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> study, respectively. The thickness of the coating was approximately 170&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. CaSiO<sub>3</sub> coatings were prepared using the same conditions as the control. Samples were ultrasonically cleaned and sterilized in acetone, ethanol and distilled water for 10&#x02009;min.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Isolation, Culture, and Identification of BM-PCs</title><p>All experiments involving animals complied fully with guidelines for animal care and use and the experimental protocol was ethically reviewed and approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of The Second Military Medical University. The BM-PCs were isolated according to previously described methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>. Briefly, thigh bones were isolated from Sprague-Dawley rats (body weight, 100&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10&#x02009;g), and bone marrow containing mononuclear cells was flushed out with Dulbecco&#x02019;s modified Eagle medium: Nutrient Mixture F-12 (DMEM/F-12, Gibco Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) using a 1&#x02009;ml syringe. The cell suspension was filtered through a 40-&#x003bc;m strainer, and the cells were centrifuged (1000&#x02009;rpm for 5&#x02009;min) and washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). The cells were resuspended in DMEM/F12 containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; Gibco Life Technologies), 100&#x02009;U/ml penicillin and 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml streptomycin (Gibco Life Technologies). The harvested cells were seeded at a density of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup>/ml in a 75-cm<sup>2</sup> tissue culture flask. The media were changed every 2&#x02013;3 days. After 7 days of primary culture, the cells were passaged and expanded for future use. Cells at passages 3&#x02013;5 were used in this study.</p><p>For BM-PCs characterization, cell surface markers were quantified by flow cytometry as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>. BM-PCs of passage 4 were harvested by treatment with 0.25% trypsin-EDTA (Gibco Life Technologies). The trypsinized cells (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> cells) were washed twice with PBS and stained with fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-conjugated mouse antihuman CD29 and CD31, phycoerythrin (PE)-conjugated mouse antihuman CD90 and allophycocyanin (APC)-conjugated CD45 (BD Biosciences, San Jose, USA). After 30&#x02009;min of incubation at room temperature, the cells were washed twice with PBS and analyzed using a BD FACS Aria II (BD Biosciences, San Jose, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Cell Proliferation and Cytotoxicity</title><p>Cell proliferation was measured using a Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8; Beyotime, China). BM-PCs were cultured on the Ti-6Al-4V control and the CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, Zn-Ca 0.1, and Zn-Ca 0.3 coatings placed individually in a 24-well culture plate at a density of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup>&#x02009;cells/cm<sup>2</sup> in growth medium. After 1, 4, 7 and 14 days, the CCK-8 stock solution (10% of the total volume) was added to each well of the 24-well plates and incubated for 4&#x02009;h at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Then, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of the solution was transferred to 96-well plates, and the absorbance was read at 450&#x02009;nm by a microplate reader (SPECTRA MAX PLUS 384 MK3, Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA). Additionally, cell cytotoxicity was confirmed by a live/dead assay kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) after culturing for 48&#x02009;h. The assay was performed according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Afterward, the stained cells were visualized using confocal laser scanning microscopy (CLSM, LeicaTCSSP5, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Osteogenic Differentiation and Mineralization</title><p>To evaluate their osteogenic capacity, BM-PCs (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> cells/well) were seeded on each coating group and cultured in osteogenic medium of DMEM/F-12 supplemented with 10% FBS, 100&#x02009;U/ml penicillin, 100&#x02009;mg/ml streptomycin, 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml ascorbic acid (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, USA), 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;M dexamethasone (Sigma-Aldrich) and 10&#x02009;mM &#x003b2;-glycerophosphate (Sigma-Aldrich). Cell differentiation and mineralization were confirmed using the alkaline phosphatase (ALP) activity, the procollagen &#x003b1;1(I) (Col-I) and osteocalcin (OCN) secretion and Alizarin red S staining as described below.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>ALP Assay and Col-I and OCN Secretion</title><p>The stable <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenol phosphate substrate was used to quantify ALP activity. BM-PCs were cultured on the Ti-6Al-4V control and the CaSiO<sub>3</sub>, Zn-Ca 0.1, and Zn-Ca0.3 coatings in osteogenic medium for 1, 7, 14, and 21 days. At each time point, the culture medium was removed, and the cells were washed with PBS and harvested in 1&#x02009;ml of universal ALP buffer (100&#x02009;mM citric acid, 100&#x02009;mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 100&#x02009;mM sodium tetraborate.10H<sub>2</sub>O, 100&#x02009;mM Tris, and 100&#x02009;mM KCl; pH 11). The cells were centrifuged at 3000&#x02009;rpm for 5&#x02009;min at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The ALP activity in the supernatants was determined following the addition of <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenyl phosphate substrate, and the reaction was stopped using 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of 0.1&#x02009;N NaOH. The absorbance was read with a microplate reader (SPECTRA MAX PLUS 384 MK3, Thermo, USA) at a wavelength of 405&#x02009;nm.</p><p>The levels of Col-I and OCN secreted into the culture medium were quantified using an enzyme-linked immunoassay (ELISA) kit (R&#x00026;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Alizarin Red Staining (ARS)</title><p>Osteogenesis was confirmed by Alizarin red S staining. The cells were seeded on different coatings and cultured in osteogenic medium. At the indicated time point, the cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 20&#x02009;min at room temperature and stained with 0.1% Alizarin Red S (Beyotime, China) at room temperature for 30&#x02009;min. Afterward, the cells were washed twice with PBS and air dried before the ARS staining was eluted with 5% perchloric acid (SCRC, Shanghai, China). The 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l solution from each well was then transferred to a 96-well plate, and the optical density (OD) was measured at 490&#x02009;nm using a spectrophotometer (SPECTRA MAX PLUS 384 MK3, Thermo, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>RNA Extraction and Quantitative Reverse Transcriptase Polymerase Chain Reaction (Q-PCR)</title><p>After seeding for 1, 7, 14 and 21 days, total RNA was extracted from BM-PCs on each coating using RNAiso Plus (TaKaRa Bio Inc., Japan) and treated with Recombinant DNase I (RNase-free) (TaKaRa Bio Inc., Japan) to remove genomic DNA contamination following the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. 500&#x02009;ng RNA was converted to cDNA with M-MLV reverse Transcriptase (Promega, WI, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The PCR reaction with a final volume of 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l contained 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of 2&#x000d7; SYBR Green PCR Master Mix, 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;M forward and reverse primers, 8&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of water, and 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of template cDNA. The PCR amplification conditions were as follows: 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min, 40 repetitions of 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;s, 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;s, and 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;s and a final extension at 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min. The specific primers used for the qPCR are listed in the Supporting Information (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Q-PCR analysis was performed on an ABI 7500 Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Life Technologies, USA). The expression of all target genes was normalized to the housekeeping gene glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) and shown as the expression relative to that of the negative control group using the comparative CT method (2<sup>&#x02212;<italic>&#x00394;&#x00394;</italic>CT</sup>). Each experiment was repeated in triplicate for each individual sample.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Western Blotting Analysis</title><p>A Western blot can be used to determine the specific protein expression in a given sample. BM-PCs in each group were lysed in RIPA buffer containing 1&#x02009;mM phenylmethane sulfonyl-fluoride (Beyotime, China). The total protein concentration of the supernatant was measured using a bicinchoninic acid (BCA) assay kit (Beijing CoWin Biotech Co. Ltd., Beijing, China) in accordance with the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g protein from each sample were separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) and transferred onto 0.22&#x02009;&#x003bc;m polyvinylidene difluoridemembranes (Millipore, Bedford, Mass, USA). After the membrane was blocked, the blots were incubated with the appropriate primary antibodies: rabbit anti-phospho-Smad2 (Ser465/467)/Smad3 (Ser423/425) (Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, USA), rabbit anti-Smad2/3 (Cell Signaling Technology), and anti-GAPDH monoclonal antibody (Novus, CO, USA) overnight at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. All primary antibodies were applied at a 1:1000 dilution. The membranes were washed three times in phosphate-buffered saline +0.1% Tween 20 (PBST) buffer and then further incubated with anti mouse/rabbit HRP conjugated secondary antibodies at 1: 4000 dilutions for 1&#x02009;h at room temperature and detected with the ECL Kit (Beijing CoWin Biotech Co. Ltd., Beijing, China). The protein bands were visualized using an Image Quant Las4000mini (GE Healthcare, UK). GAPDH served as an internal control.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Inhibition of TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad Signaling</title><p>To assess the role of TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad signaling in the regulation of osteogenic differentiation of BM-PCs cultured on the Zn-modified coatings, on the second day of culture, BM-PCs on the different coatings were treated with or without 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;M SB431542 (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, USA). SB431542 is a selective inhibitor of activin receptor-like kinase ALK5 (T&#x003b2;RI), whereas Smad2 and Smad3 are substrates for ALK5. SB431542 has been demonstrated to be a specific inhibitor of the TGF-&#x003b2;/Smad pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup>. After 21 days, the BM-PCs were collected, and Smad2/3and phospho-Smad2/Smad3 proteins were detected by Western blotting.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Ovariectomized Rabbits</title><p>Forty-five mature female New Zealand white rabbits (90&#x02013;100 days old, 2&#x02013;2.5&#x02009;kg) were used for this experiment. The use of animals and the surgical procedures were approved by the Institutional Animal Welfare Committee of The Second Military Medical University. To induce an osteopenic model, the rabbits were subjected to bilateral ovariectomy (OVX) through a ventral incision under general anesthesia with an intraperitoneal injection of sodium pentobarbital (30&#x02009;mg/kg body weight). The incision was closed layer by layer. After the surgery, the rabbits were injected intramuscularly with methylprednisolone sodium succinate (MPS) (Pfizer Manufacturing Belgium NV) dissolved in 0.9% benzyl alcohol at a dosage of 1.0&#x02009;mg/kg/day for 4 consecutive months. Sham-operated rabbits were surgically operated on similarly to OVX rabbits except that the ovaries were not cauterized. At the end of the treatment, the osteopenic state in ovariectomized rabbits was confirmed by micro-computed tomography (micro-CT) imaging of the proximal tibia.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Surgical Procedure</title><p>After osteopenic animal models were created, each ovariectomized rabbit underwent general anaesthesia by the intraperitoneal injection of sodium pentobarbital (30&#x02009;mg/kg body weight). A linear skin incision that was approximately 2&#x02009;cm long in the distal femoral epiphysis was made laterally, and the lateral femoral condyle was exposed by blunt dissection of the muscles. Then, circular holes (2-mm diameter, 10-mm depth) were created using a surgical electric drill at a slow speed. During drilling, physiological saline was supplied to remove bone shards and rinse the wounded area to stop the bleeding. Forty ovariectomized rabbits were randomly divided into five groups (8 rabbits per group), and the rabbits were implanted with (1) uncoated Ti-6Al-4V (control), (2) HA-coated Ti-6Al-4V, (3) CaSiO<sub>3</sub>-coated Ti-6Al-4V, (4) Ca<sub>2</sub>ZnSi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>-coated Ti-6Al-4V (Zn-Ca 0.1) and (5) Ca<sub>2</sub>ZnSi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>-coated Ti-6Al-4V (Zn-Ca 0.3). A total of four implants were implanted into the femur of each rabbit. Two implants were inserted into the femur of the left hind leg and another two into the femur of the right hind leg. When the implants were then gently placed to fill the grilled defects according to group allocation. Subsequently, the incision was closed with absorbable sutures (Marlin, Germany), and antibiotics and analgesics were injected intramuscularly. At each time point (1, 2 and 3 months after surgery), ovariectomized rabbits were euthanized and specimens were harvested for micro-computed tomography (micro-CT) analysis and histological examination.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Micro-CT Examination</title><p>The femoral heads were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 24&#x02009;h at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. A micro-CT imaging system (SkyScan1076, Brukermicro CT, USA) was used to evaluate the new bone formation within the defect region. The acquisition settings were 49&#x02009;kV and 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;A with a spatial resolution of 35&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. A consistent volume of interest (VOI) with a diameter of 3&#x02009;mm and a height of 4&#x02009;mm was chosen to evaluate the level of bone regeneration and was reconstructed three-dimensionally using Micview software. The bone mineral density (BMD), bone volume/total volume of bone (BV/TV), trabecular number (Tb.N), trabecular thickness (Tb.Th), and trabecular separation (Tb.Sp) were automatically determined to evaluate the new bone formation within the defect region of the femoral heads. All the morphometric analysis was performed using SkyScan CTVOX 2.1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Histopathological Examination</title><p>After micro-CT scanning, the defective femoral tissue was fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 3 days, dehydrated in a series of graded concentrations of ethanol from 70 to 100% for 1&#x02009;day at each concentration, exposed to dimethyl benzene and then embedded in methyl methacrylate without decalcification., Each specimen was then cut perpendicular to the long axis of implants into 3&#x02009;&#x003bc;m thick sections along the central axis of the implant using a cutting machine (EXAKT 300 CPB and System, Norderstedt, Germany). The sections from each group were stained with 1% toluidine blue and observed by light microscopy (BX51; Olympus, Japan) for histomorphometry.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>For statistical analysis, Levene&#x02019;s test was performed to determine the homogeneity of variance for all data, and then one-way analysis of variance followed by Tukey&#x02019;s or Tamhane&#x02019;s T2 posthoc test for multiple comparison was performed for the comparisons between different groups. All statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism 5.0 (San Diego, CA, USA). The results were considered significant at *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, very significant at **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 and extremely significant at ***<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001. All data were expressed as the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (SD).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec27"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2017_3661_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supporting information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Jiangming Yu, Lizhang Xu and Kai Li contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>
<bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at doi:10.1038/s41598-017-03661-5
</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 81301537) and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>J.Y., L.X. and K.L. designed the scheme and wrote the manuscript under the guidance of X.Z., X.C., M.W. and X.Y., N.X., Y.X., and Y.W. performed the calculations and analyzed the results. X.C., M.W. and X.Y. participated in the discussions, and provided valuable suggestions. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corrosion of metal orthopaedic implants</article-title><source>J. Bone Joint Surg. Am.</source><year>1998</year><volume>80A</volume><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/00004623-199802000-00015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cesar Neto</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sallum</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nociti</surname><given-names>jFH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estrogen deficiency affects bone healing around titanium implants: a histometric study in rats</article-title><source>Implant dent.</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.ID.0000099750.26582.4B</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14752971?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14752971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hydroxylapatite coating of porous implants improves bone ingrowth and interface attachment strength</article-title><source>J. Biomed. Mater. Res.</source><year>1992</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbm.820260803</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1429760?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1429760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biomaterial strategies for engineering implants for enhanced osseointegration and bone repair</article-title><source>Adv. Drug Del. Rev.</source><year>2015</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addr.2015.03.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aebli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> comparison of the osseointegration of vacuum plasma sprayed titanium- and hydroxyapatite-coated implants</article-title><source>J. Biomed. Mater. Res. Part A</source><year>2003</year><volume>66A</volume><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbm.a.10508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction plasma sprayed nano hydroxyapatite coatings on titanium for orthopaedic and dental implants</article-title><source>Surf. Coat. Technol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>2785</fpage><lpage>2792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.surfcoat.2010.10.042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21552358?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21552358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biocompatibility of electrophoretical deposition of nanostructured hydroxyapatite coating on roughen titanium surface: <italic>In vitro</italic> evaluation using mesenchymal stem cells</article-title><source>J. Biomed. Mater. Res. Part B</source><year>2007</year><volume>82B</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbm.b.30720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early bone apposition <italic>in vivo</italic> on plasma-sprayed and electrochemically deposited hydroxyapatite coatings on titanium alloy</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>4192</fpage><lpage>4203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2006.03.034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16618502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16618502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Svehla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Morphometric and mechanical evaluation of titanium implant integration: Comparison of five surface structures</article-title><source>J. Biomed. Mater. Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-4636(200007)51:1&#x0003c;15::AID-JBM3&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10813740?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10813740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effects of combined human parathyroid hormone (1&#x02013;34) and simvastatin treatment on the interface of hydroxyapatite-coated titanium rods implanted into osteopenic rats femurs</article-title><source>J. Mater. Sci-Mater. M.</source><year>2016</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10856-015-5650-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26610931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intermittent administration of human parathyroid hormone (1&#x02013;34) increases fixation of strontium-doped hydroxyapatite coating titanium implants via electrochemical deposition in ovariectomized rat femur</article-title><source>J. Biomater. Appl.</source><year>2016</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>952</fpage><lpage>960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0885328215610898</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26482573?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26482573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Uenoyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mashima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugioka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remodeling of bone around hydroxyapatite and titanium in experimental osteoporosis</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>1994</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0142-9612(94)90189-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8161651?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8161651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Osteoporosis and biomaterial osteointegration</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><year>2004</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0753-3322(04)00126-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15511604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15511604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of osteopenia on the osteointegration of different biomaterials: histomorphometric study in rats</article-title><source>J. Mater. Sci-Mater. M.</source><year>2000</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008932303913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15348388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Osteoblast response to porous titanium surfaces coated with zincsubstituted hydroxyapatite</article-title><source>Or Surg Or Med Or Pa.</source><year>2012</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tripleo.2011.02.049</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22676822?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22676822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of nutritional zinc in the prevention of osteoporosis</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biochem.</source><year>2010</year><volume>338</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11010-009-0358-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20035439?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20035439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term implantation of zinc-releasing calcium phosphate ceramics in rabbit femora</article-title><source>J. Biomed. Mater. Res. Part A</source><year>2003</year><volume>65A</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbm.a.10524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staiger</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietak</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Huadmai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnesium and its alloys as orthopedic biomaterials: A review</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1728</fpage><lpage>1734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2005.10.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16246414?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16246414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of strontium-substituted hydroxyapatite coating on implant fixation in ovariectomized rats</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>9006</fpage><lpage>9014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2010.07.112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20800275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20800275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamitakahara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtsuki</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Inada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of ZnO addition on bioactive CaO-SiO<sub>2</sub>-P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>-CaF<sub>2</sub> glass-ceramics containing apatite and wollastonite</article-title><source>Acta Biomater.</source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actbio.2006.03.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16765885?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16765885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zreiqat</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological response of human bone cells to zinc-modified Ca-Si-based ceramics</article-title><source>Acta Biomater.</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1487</fpage><lpage>1497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actbio.2008.04.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18501689?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18501689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caplan</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruder</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells: building blocks for molecular medicine in the 21st century</article-title><source>Trends Mol. Med.</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1471-4914(01)02016-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11378515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11378515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yousefi</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prospect of Stem Cells in Bone Tissue Engineering: A Review</article-title><source>Stem Cells Int.</source><year>2016</year><volume>2016</volume><fpage>6180487</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/6180487</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26880976?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26880976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gold nanoparticles stimulate differentiation and mineralization of primary osteoblasts through the ERK/MAPK signaling pathway</article-title><source>Mater. Sci. Eng. C-Mater. Biol. Appl.</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msec.2014.04.042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25063094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25063094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamil</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Banik</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Asaduzzaman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGF-beta/BMP signaling and other molecular events: regulation of osteoblastogenesis and bone formation</article-title><source>Bone Res.</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/boneres.2015.5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>WX</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multi-Walled Carbon Nanotubes Promote Cementoblast Differentiation and Mineralization through the TGF-beta/Smad Signaling Pathway</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3188</fpage><lpage>3201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms16023188</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25648319?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25648319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic compression of rabbit adipose-derived stem cells transfected with insulin-like growth factor 1 in chitosan/gelatin scaffolds induces chondrogenesis and matrix biosynthesis</article-title><source>J. Cell. Physiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>2003</fpage><lpage>2012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcp.22927</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21751209?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21751209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zreiqat</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of surface chemistry modification of titanium alloy on signalling pathways in human osteoblasts</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>7579</fpage><lpage>7586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2005.05.024</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16002135?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16002135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced Osseointegration of Hierarchical Micro/Nanotopographic Titanium Fabricated by Microarc Oxidation and Electrochemical Treatment</article-title><source>ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces</source><year>2016</year><fpage>3840</fpage><lpage>3852</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of integrin-linked kinase/beta-catenin pathway in the enhanced MG63 differentiation by micro/nano-textured topography</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2013</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2012.10.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23107296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23107296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Osteogenic differentiation of bone marrow MSCs by beta-tricalcium phosphate stimulating macrophages via BMP2 signalling pathway</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2014</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1507</fpage><lpage>1518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2013.11.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24268199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24268199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ripamonti</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Crooks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Khoah</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roden</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The induction of bone formation by coral-derived calcium carbonate/hydroxyapatite constructs</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1428</fpage><lpage>1439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2008.10.065</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19081131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19081131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bone morphogenetic protein Smads signaling in mesenchymal stem cells affected by osteoinductive calcium phosphate ceramics</article-title><source>J. Biomed. Mater. Res. Part A</source><year>2015</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>1001</fpage><lpage>1010</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbm.a.35242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ripamonti</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Roden</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Renton</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteoinductive hydroxyapatite-coated titanium implants</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2012</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>3813</fpage><lpage>3823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2012.01.050</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22364700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22364700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of osteoblast-like cell responses to calcium silicate and tricalcium phosphate ceramics <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>J. Biomed. Mater. Res. Part B.</source><year>2007</year><volume>80B</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbm.b.30582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reconstruction of calvarial defect of rabbits using porous calcium silicate bioactive ceramics</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2008</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>2588</fpage><lpage>2596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2008.03.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18378303?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18378303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Soeparto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zreiqat</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incorporation of titanium into calcium silicate improved their chemical stability and biological properties</article-title><source>J. Biomed. Mater. Res. Part A</source><year>2008</year><volume>86A</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jbm.a.31623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bioinorganics in Bioactive Calcium Silicate Ceramics for Bone Tissue Repair: Bioactivity and Biological Properties</article-title><source>J. Ceram. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excellent stability of plasma-sprayed bioactive Ca3ZrSi2O9 ceramic coating on Ti-6Al-4V</article-title><source>Appl. Surf. Sci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>256</volume><fpage>4677</fpage><lpage>4681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsusc.2010.02.071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasma sprayed wollastonite/TiO2 composite coatings on titanium alloys</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2002</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>4065</fpage><lpage>4077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0142-9612(02)00143-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12182308?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12182308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of Zn Content on Crystal Structure, Cytocompatibility, Antibacterial Activity, and Chemical Stability in Zn-Modified Calcium Silicate Coatings</article-title><source>J. Therm. Spray Technol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>965</fpage><lpage>973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11666-013-9938-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kutikov</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An amphiphilic degradable polymer/hydroxyapatite composite with enhanced handling characteristics promotes osteogenic gene expression in bone marrow stromal cells</article-title><source>Acta Biomater.</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>8354</fpage><lpage>8364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actbio.2013.06.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23791675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23791675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmieri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carinci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolfarini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene expression of human osteoblasts cells on chemically treated surfaces of Ti-6Al-4V-ELI</article-title><source>Mater. Sci. Eng. C-Mater. Biol. Appl.</source><year>2015</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.msec.2015.03.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25842132?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25842132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of the dissolved zinc ion and reactive oxygen species in cytotoxicity of ZnO nanoparticles</article-title><source>Toxicol Lett.</source><year>2010</year><volume>199</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxlet.2010.10.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20934491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20934491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aina</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Malavasi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pla</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Munaron</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Morterra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zinc-containing bioactive glasses: Surface reactivity and behaviour towards endothelial cells</article-title><source>Acta Biomater.</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1211</fpage><lpage>1222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actbio.2008.10.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19042164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19042164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lusvardi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Properties of zinc releasing surfaces for clinical applications</article-title><source>J. Biomater. Appl.</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0885328207079731</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17623710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17623710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>In Vitro</italic> and <italic>In Vivo</italic> Evaluation of Zinc-Modified Ca-Si-Based Ceramic Coating for Bone Implants</article-title><source>Plos One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/annotation/2212a861-273a-4c34-816a-ead5d0d8a7f5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hu, D. <italic>et al</italic>. Different response of osteoblastic cells to Mg2+, Zn2+ and Sr2+ doped calcium silicate coatings. <italic>J Mater Sci</italic>-<italic>Mater M</italic>. <bold>27</bold> (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Grayson</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stem cell-based approaches to engineering vascularized bone</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Eng.</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coche.2013.12.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Zn-Releasing FHA Coating and Its Enhanced Osseointegration Ability</article-title><source>J. Am. Ceram. Soc.</source><year>2011</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>261</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synergistic effects of Nell-1 and BMP-2 on the osteogenic differentiation of myoblasts</article-title><source>J. Bone Miner. Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>918</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1359/jbmr.070312</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17352654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17352654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Granchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene Expression Patterns Related to Osteogenic Differentiation of Bone Marrow-Derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells During <italic>Ex Vivo</italic> Expansion</article-title><source>Tissue Engineering Part C-Methods</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ten.tec.2009.0405</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19686055?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19686055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity and increased bone marrow stem cell functions of Zn-incorporated TiO2 coatings on titanium</article-title><source>Acta Biomater.</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>904</fpage><lpage>915</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actbio.2011.09.031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22023752?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22023752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fabrication and evaluation of Zn containing fluoridated hydroxyapatite layer with Zn release ability</article-title><source>Acta Biomater.</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actbio.2007.08.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17942380?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17942380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storrie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Stupp</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellular response to zinc-containing organoapatite: An <italic>in vitro</italic> study of proliferation, alkaline phosphatase activity and biomineralization</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>5492</fpage><lpage>5499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2005.01.043</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15860205?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15860205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulterer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression profiling of human mesenchymal stem cells derived from bone marrow during expansion and osteoblast differentiation</article-title><source>Bmc Genomics</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>15</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-8-70</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17214893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benoit</surname><given-names>DSW</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Anseth</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multifunctional hydrogels that promote osteogenic human mesenchymal stem cell differentiation through stimulation and sequestering of bone morphogenic protein 2</article-title><source>Adv. Funct. Mater.</source><year>2007</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2085</fpage><lpage>2093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adfm.200700012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18688288?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18688288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heldin</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>tenDijke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGF-beta signalling from cell membrane to nucleus through SMAD proteins</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>390</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/37284</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9393997?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9393997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leboy</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Smad-Runx interactions during chondrocyte maturation</article-title><source>J. Bone Joint Surg. Am.</source><year>2001</year><volume>83A</volume><fpage>S15</fpage><lpage>S22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ducy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Geoffroy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridall</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Karsenty</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osf2/Cbfa1: A transcriptional activator of osteoblast differentiation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80257-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9182762?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9182762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Runx2 Protein Expression Utilizes the Runx2 P1 Promoter to Establish Osteoprogenitor Cell Number for Normal Bone Formation</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>30057</fpage><lpage>30070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.241505</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21676869?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21676869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cbfa1, a candidate gene for cleidocranial dysplasia syndrome, is essential for osteoblast differentiation and bone development</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80259-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9182764?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9182764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sowa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of menin, the product of the multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 gene, inhibits the commitment of multipotential mesenchymal stem cells into the osteoblast lineage</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>21058</fpage><lpage>21069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M302044200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12649288?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12649288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of bone regeneration by gene delivery of BMP2/Runx2 bicistronic vector into adipose-derived stromal cells</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>5652</fpage><lpage>5659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2010.03.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20413153?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20413153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Smad3-dependent nuclear translocation of beta-catenin is required for TGF-beta 1-induced proliferation of bone marrow-derived adult human mesenchymal stem cells</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>666</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1388806</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16543220?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16543220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanotechnology for treating osteoporotic vertebral fractures</article-title><source>International Journal of Nanomedicine</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>5139</fpage><lpage>5157</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26316746?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26316746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stromsoe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fracture fixation problems in osteoporosis</article-title><source>Injury.</source><year>2004</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.injury.2003.08.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14736465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14736465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of zinc in bone formation and bone resorption</article-title><source>J Trace Elem Exp Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1520-670X(1998)11:2/3&#x0003c;119::AID-JTRA5&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozawa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Uematsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zinc suppresses IL-6 synthesis by prostaglandin F-2 alpha in osteoblasts: Inhibition of phospholipase C and phospholipase D</article-title><source>J. Cell. Biochem.</source><year>2002</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.10166</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11968002?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11968002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kassis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation of mesenchymal stem cells from G-CSF-mobilized human peripheral blood using fibrin microbeads</article-title><source>Bone. Marrow. Transpl.</source><year>2006</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>976</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bmt.1705358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cai, Y. T., Liu, T. S., Fang, F., Xiong, C. L. &#x00026; Shen, S. L. Comparisons of Mouse Mesenchymal Stem Cells in Primary Adherent Culture of Compact Bone Fragments and Whole Bone Marrow. <italic>Stem Cells Int</italic>. <bold>8</bold> (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lysy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Najimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokal</surname><given-names>EFM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Native umbilical cord matrix stem cells express hepatic markers and differentiate into hepatocyte-like cells</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2008</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2007.12.024</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18243183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18243183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inman</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SB-431542 is a potent and specific inhibitor of transforming growth factor-beta superfamily type I activin receptor-like kinase (ALK) receptors ALK4, ALK5, and ALK7</article-title><source>Mol. Pharmacol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.62.1.65</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12065756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12065756</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>